<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plea for the common-laws of England or an answer to a book entituled, A good work for a good magistrate: or, a short cut to a great quiet. (Published by Mr. Hugh Peters:) So far as concerns his proposals touching the said laws. By R. Vaughan of Grays-Inne.</title>
            <author>Vaughan, Rice.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95831</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V135</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1379_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209371</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868251</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868251</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169891</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95831)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169891)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 180:E1379[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plea for the common-laws of England or an answer to a book entituled, A good work for a good magistrate: or, a short cut to a great quiet. (Published by Mr. Hugh Peters:) So far as concerns his proposals touching the said laws. By R. Vaughan of Grays-Inne.</title>
                  <author>Vaughan, Rice.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Francis Tyton, and are to be sold at his shop, at the three Daggers in Fleetstreet, near the Inner Temple-gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Peters, Hugh, 1598-1660.  Good work for a good magistrate. Or a short cut to great quiet.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 3d".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Peters, Hugh, 1598-1660. --  Good work for a good magistrate. Or a short cut to great quiet.</term>
               <term>Law --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169891:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PLEA FOR THE Common-Laws OF England: OR, An Anſwer to a BOOK <hi>ENTIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LED,</hi> A good work for a good Magiſtrate: Or, a ſhort Cut to great quiet. (Publiſhed by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Hugh Peters:</hi>) So far as concerns his Propoſals touching the ſaid Laws. By <hi>R. Vaughan</hi> of <hi>Grays-Inne.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>—Tractent fabrilia fabri.</l>
               <l>Ignorantia Juris litigioſa, non Scientia. <hi>Cicero.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Francis Tyton,</hi> and are to ſold at his Shop, at the three Daggers in Fleetſtreet, near the Inner Temple-gate. 1651.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_Parliament_of_England">
            <pb facs="tcp:169891:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169891:2"/>
            <head>To the Parliament OF ENGLAND, The SUPREAM Power of this Common-Wealth.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Mr. <hi>P.</hi> hath dedicated his Book to you; ſo doth the Author hereof his, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing no better earthly Tribunal to be judged by. Mr. <hi>P.</hi> writes againſt the Law out of a <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice,</hi> and I out of <hi>affection</hi> to it; we may be both byaſſed: you are the Judges of it. I wiſh no greater earthly
<pb facs="tcp:169891:3"/>Happineſs to this Nation then the continuance of the <hi>antient Common Laws</hi> of it, (ſome exuberancies of it being lopt off, and ſome other parts of it, which by a non-uſe are buryed in oblivion being taken away) and the frequent ſupply of good and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Miniſters of it; for our Law in it ſelf is one of the moſt excellent <hi>humane</hi> Laws that any Nation in the World hath; The Common-Laws of this Land were never originally the <hi>Dictates</hi> of any <hi>Conquerours Sword,</hi> or the <hi>Placita</hi> or <hi>good will</hi> and <hi>pleaſure</hi> of any <hi>King</hi> of this Nation, or to ſpeak <hi>impartially</hi> and <hi>freely,</hi> the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults of <hi>any Parliament</hi> that ever ſat in this Land, but it was a <hi>Lex non ſcripta,</hi> and a <hi>Jus</hi> (as the <hi>Civilian</hi> ſaith of his Law) <hi>quod uſus approbavit; nam diuturni mores conſenſu utentium comprobati, legem imitantur:</hi> it is now a <hi>Lex ſcripta,</hi> and we ſay, That it conſiſts of laudable and righteous Cuſtoms, iterated and multiplyed
<pb facs="tcp:169891:3"/>in their common uſe among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this Land time out of minde; and ſo to us carryed down through the ſucceſſive Ages of many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years ago, upon the two wheels of <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Conveniency;</hi> ſo that what of it was approved at firſt, and hath ſince wanted theſe two helps to bring it down to us, hath by a <hi>tacit conſent</hi> of the people <hi>(i.e.)</hi> by the <hi>neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect</hi> and <hi>non-uſe</hi> of it, loſt the <hi>force</hi> of a Law: And the other part of it, which by long <hi>uſe, experience,</hi> and <hi>tryal,</hi> was found <hi>beneficial,</hi> and for <hi>common good,</hi> was deſervedly <hi>baptized</hi> with the name of <hi>Common-Law,</hi> it being almoſt a comprehenſive <hi>Rule and meaſure of all mens actions in this Land,</hi> how divers ſoever Actions and Accidents be, and how full ſoever of motion and mutations, which (I humbly ſubmit to your wiſdoms) whether Mr. <hi>Ps.</hi> new Law can reach. Beſides, the Common-Law hath been ſo far <hi>honoured</hi> by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
<pb facs="tcp:169891:4"/>Parliments in this Land, as to have ſeveral Statutes made in affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of it; ſo that it like is gold (I will not ſay ſeven, but ſeven times ſeven) tried, I ſhall trouble you no longer. But take leave and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your faithful Servant</hi> R. Vaughan.</signed>
               <dateline>Grays <date>Inne 20. of <hi>June.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:169891:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To M.</hi> Hugh Peters.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAD not your <hi>Pen awaked</hi> the evil ſpirit of the Paſquillers of this Age, and alſo given <hi>Sail</hi> to the wiſhes of ſuch that would have the <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Innocency</hi> of our Law to have no ſafe retreat for <hi>it ſelf</hi> &amp; its <hi>honeſt</hi> profeſſors from their debaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: I ſhould not have <hi>ventured</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo <hi>early a Remedy</hi> againſt your Books getting eſteem in the <hi>world:</hi> for I am told, that it is <hi>better</hi> and <hi>ſafer</hi> to meet a <hi>danger</hi> when it firſt <hi>moves</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, then to encounter it in its <hi>nearer approaches;</hi> every ſtep and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs it makes, rendring it more <hi>invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible,</hi> and them more <hi>unſafe</hi> that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it; eſpecially if the danger be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded with the hurrying ſwindge of ſuch men as <hi>will do a thing,</hi> becauſe they <hi>will do</hi> it, and have not other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for what they do: I am ſorry you
<pb facs="tcp:169891:5"/>ſhould open ſo wide a Caſement for evil men to ſee the <hi>face</hi> and <hi>complexion</hi> of your ſpirit, as to our Law, which (you may aſſure your ſelf) is not ſo clear and ſerene from the <hi>ſpots</hi> of miſtakes and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regularities, as I could wiſh his were who hath done ſo much ſervice to the Parliament as you have done: If I make a <hi>ſeverer</hi> conſtruction of your <hi>meaning</hi> then you intended, you may rather thank your <hi>own words,</hi> which made ſo <hi>falſe a report</hi> of your ſenſe and meaning to my underſtanding, then blame me, who could not find out a better <hi>Index</hi> of the <hi>ſpirit</hi> and <hi>reaſon</hi> of what you propoſed. Had I been to deal with an adverſary to the Common Cauſe we both have adhered to, I aſſure you I ſhould have treated and handled him in a <hi>rougher accent,</hi> if I had had the like advantage as I have againſt you: I hope therefore you will be ſatisfied, that this anſwer is not out of <hi>diſreſpect</hi> to you, but out of <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity</hi> to juſtifie that which is <hi>good</hi> and <hi>innocent,</hi> againſt which you writ,
<pb facs="tcp:169891:5"/>becauſe you have <hi>heard</hi> ill of it, and not becauſe you know <hi>experimentally</hi> in it thoſe miſchiefs which you propoſe to be reformed. I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sir, Yours affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately. R. Vaughan.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Grayes Inn,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>20.</hi> June, <hi>1651.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:169891:6"/>
            <head>An Introduction.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Should never have trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the <hi>Preſs</hi> with thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> anſwer to Mr. <hi>P.</hi> his Book did I not know the aptneſs of <hi>wel-diſpoſed</hi> and <hi>cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous</hi> people to adore the <hi>dictates</hi> of men of his <hi>Profeſſion</hi> and <hi>converſation,</hi> and to take them up upon truſt out of the respect they have of their <hi>perſons</hi> (and of his more especially, whoſe indevors have been <hi>conſtant,</hi> and whoſe bent hath always been <hi>ſet</hi> for the <hi>publick</hi> good of this Commonwealth.) For I ſee not any thing in his Book as to the <hi>Law</hi> (&amp; I will not <hi>meddle</hi> beyond the <hi>bounds</hi> of that profeſſion, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> am a <hi>mean</hi> Profeſſor, and ſhall be glad of any occaſion to aſſert its <hi>juſtice</hi> and <hi>innocency</hi>) that can tempt a <hi>ſerious</hi> man to put Pen to
<pb facs="tcp:169891:6"/>Paper to give it <hi>anſwer;</hi> it being <hi>rudis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digeſtaque moles,</hi> a throng or croud of <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marſhalled expreſſions,</hi> full of contradictions, repetitions and incoherencies, like the <hi>Tohu vabohu</hi> in the beginning of the <hi>Creation;</hi> now I ſay, becauſe the <hi>well-meaning</hi> or <hi>plain honeſt man,</hi> to whom his Book may come, may not <hi>exclaim</hi> againſt the preſent Laws (which they know not, and which yet are their birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, and one of the greateſt earthly Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>dges they have,) becauſe Mr. <hi>P.</hi> is pleaſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>undervalue</hi> them, upon a very <hi>ſlender</hi> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o knowledge of its <hi>foundations;</hi> I have thus ventured to be publike. I may ſafely affirm the Common-Law is not ſo bad as he thinks it: it is no ſuch <hi>jus vagum &amp; incertum,</hi> no ſuch <hi>leaden Rule</hi> as gives neither <hi>ſecurity</hi> to mens <hi>perſons,</hi> or <hi>certainty</hi> to their <hi>proprieties,</hi> but it doth conſiſt <hi>ex Regulis de Jure fabricatis;</hi> it is the <hi>product of length of time, and varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of occurrences</hi> ſuted and ſquared, (or (at the worſt) not inconſiſtent) with the Rules of <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Right Reaſon;</hi> and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever part of the Law doth not derive its <hi>Parentage</hi> hence, is contrary to, or inconſiſtent herewith, is by all Lawyers adjudged to be <hi>caſhiered</hi> out of their approbation or counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ance, as its refuſe and excreſcences, and
<pb facs="tcp:169891:7"/>eſteemed an obſolete and uſeleſs thing: now that Mr. <hi>P.</hi> ſhould be its adverſary, and call it the monuments of Tyranny, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn it to the Faggot, without juſt cauſe, is hard: I have therefore endeavoured in a can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did way to <hi>undeceive</hi> thoſe, who may gain credulity with him, ſo far as concerns the Law in his Book, and (if it may be) to <hi>reconcile</hi> him to his wronged (though inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent) <hi>friend,</hi> and I lay theſe rude and ſud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> conceptions at the <hi>feet</hi> of the ſame <hi>trib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> as he hath done, the Parliament of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That in his Book he holds that, which with ſome men is a maxime, <hi>Legentem oportet credere,</hi> I will not make ſo ſevere a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of his words as to affirm (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I know him too well, to be ſo unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table towards him) yet I muſt ſay that he ſeems nothing leſs (as to the greateſt part of what he writes touching the Law) then to impoſe upon mens intellects, that which carries very little <hi>hint</hi> of Scripture, and <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour</hi> of reaſon along with it; we live now in a <hi>free</hi> Commonwealth, where we hope there will be allowed no <hi>ſuch dictators:</hi> As our L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> hath not any <hi>Principum placita</hi> for any of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> foundations (which the Civil Law (that is
<pb facs="tcp:169891:7"/>much admired by Mr. <hi>P.</hi>) hath) ſo it will not admit of <hi>Clericorum placita,</hi> which his Book ſeems to impoſe upon us. There is no Law this day in the world, that doth ſecure a mans <hi>Rem &amp; perſonam</hi> with more impregnable <hi>fences</hi> againſt wrong and incroachment, then the <hi>Common Law</hi> of <hi>England</hi> doth; and I will dare to ſay, gives ſpeedier relief notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the quick dispatches and deciſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ens rights, that are pretended to be made by the Civil Laws, if thoſe may be credited, that have had the experience of both; our Law may be truly ſaid to be the <hi>reſult</hi> of ſoundeſt reaſon, and it is ſo; for it was <hi>ſifted</hi> through the <hi>Sive</hi> of many <hi>ſucceſſive Ages;</hi> and yet I dare not but ſay that it may have ſome <hi>chaff</hi> ſtil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in it, (nay I know it hath) yet the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Authority</hi> are by little and little <hi>ventila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> that chaff away; it cannot be done all <hi>at once,</hi> and it is not to be done without <hi>much conſideration,</hi> leaſt by plucking the <hi>Tares</hi> from amongst it, the <hi>Wheat</hi> be pluckt up alſo; and this Age doth afford many honeſt, able and wiſe Iudges and Profeſſors of it, that will moſt <hi>willingly</hi> and <hi>impartially</hi> help to ſever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween its <hi>Corruption</hi> and <hi>Conſtitutions;</hi> and Mr. <hi>P.</hi> who hath <hi>ſaid</hi> much in his <hi>haſte</hi> againſt it (were he better acquainted with its
<pb facs="tcp:169891:8"/>
               <hi>principles</hi>) I believe would <hi>unſay</hi> what he hath ſaid upon a more <hi>deliberate review</hi> of what he hath written and publiſhed. He hath propoſed in his Poſtſcript of his Book, <hi>ſect. 6. That no Book ſhould be publiſhed, or come to publike view, which ſhould not paſs the approbation of ſome judicious men in every faculty.</hi> Had he obſerved this rule himſelf, I dare ſay, his Book had hardly, (if ever) ſeen the Preſs when he muſt have conſulted ſome of moſt Profeſſions about it, &amp; had their conſents. I do not marvel that he hath ſo much tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Rules of Reaſon in this point, when I conſider he ſo unadviſedly <hi>meddles</hi> beyond the <hi>line</hi> and <hi>limits</hi> of his own <hi>calling,</hi> and ſpeaks againſt thoſe things which he never had ſo narrow inſpection into, as he <hi>ought to have,</hi> that will write of their <hi>defects</hi> or <hi>corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> It is <hi>uſual</hi> with God, in the <hi>courſe</hi> of his <hi>providence</hi> to permit men to <hi>lapſe into ſtrange and ridiculous abſurdities,</hi> when they <hi>ruſh</hi> upon the <hi>reformation</hi> of thoſe Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which they have but a weak knowledge of, and of which they have <hi>hardly</hi> taken the <hi>rudeſt</hi> view or proſpect. The <hi>Harmony</hi> of the World lies in the <hi>diverſity</hi> of Profeſſions, bounded with their <hi>particular limits:</hi> and in the <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual</hi> ſubordination of the one unto the other;
<pb facs="tcp:169891:8"/>And herein is the <hi>infinite wiſdom</hi> of God ſeen moſt excellently that he hath appointed <hi>every</hi> man his <hi>place,</hi> and made him <hi>Steward</hi> of ſome part of the Creation, and a <hi>diſtinct miniſter</hi> of his Providence, the <hi>beauty</hi> whereof doth much <hi>ſhine</hi> in mens <hi>keeping</hi> within the <hi>Circle</hi> of thoſe Callings and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions to which God (by a <hi>wiſe ſteerage</hi> of their <hi>diſpoſitions,</hi> and by <hi>diverſifying</hi> the <hi>tendencies</hi> of their affections hath <hi>ſhaped</hi> and <hi>timber'd</hi> their Spirits. I would not be thought to ſpeak this as a <hi>barr</hi> to any man from a <hi>rational and generous Inquirie</hi> into <hi>other</hi> Profeſſions then his <hi>own</hi> (provided he be not more <hi>abroad</hi> then at <hi>home,</hi> where he <hi>ſhould be,</hi>) but to adviſe men from a raſh cenſure of what they know not, and from taking up againſt any Profeſſion thoſe <hi>faint</hi> Arguments of men, (viz.) <hi>clamours</hi> and <hi>calumnies,</hi> the common <hi>ſanctuary</hi> and <hi>refuge</hi> of ſuch who are either <hi>malitious,</hi> or (as to the things they ſpeak or write againſt) <hi>blind</hi> in the <hi>colours</hi> of good and evil. Mr. <hi>P.</hi> in the Title Page of his Book, tels the Reader, that <hi>facile eſt inventis addere;</hi> I muſt confeſs, when I was going to read it, I expected ſome thing in the Reformation of the Law, that was a <hi>res inventa;</hi> but was ſo <hi>foyled</hi> in my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation,
<pb facs="tcp:169891:9"/>that I found nothing new offered, that is worthy a meaner conſideration then that of them to whom he dedicates his Book; for either he hath propoſed that which was <hi>many years before propoſed,</hi> and is now under Conſideration in <hi>Parliament</hi> to reform; or what is <hi>already</hi> provided by <hi>old Laws</hi> long ſince enacted, and want nothing but the <hi>power of the Parliament</hi> to enliven them, and to give them a <hi>Reſurrection</hi> from under the <hi>naſty rubbiſh</hi> of neglect (where it hath been long interred) into a more <hi>vigorous</hi> actuation and livelineſs; for what elſe Mr. <hi>P.</hi> hath in his Book, it is either (as I humbly conceive) <hi>perplext</hi> and <hi>obſcure, impertinent, impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> or but <hi>unſeaſonably</hi> propoſed: but herein I will not be mine own Judge, becauſe the dint of Mr. <hi>Ps.</hi> Book is againſt my own Profeſſion; and now we will ſee what his Propoſals to the Parliament hold forth, and ſubmit it to the conſideration of the beſt and wiſeſt men. And whatſoever ſhall be the cenſure and judgment of good and wiſe men touching theſe ſudden lines of mine, I ſhall quietly and without contradiction ſit under the Majeſty and Authority of their Sentence.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169891:9"/>
            <head>Having thus far made my introduction to Mr. <hi>P.</hi> his Propoſals for a new method of Laws for this Commonwealth; I come now to anſwer his parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Propoſitions.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat Mr. <hi>P.</hi> hath publiſhed all and more then he knows touching the Law, I verily believe; but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be willing to learn what he knows not, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell; had he known the good of it as well as exclaimed againſt what he conceives (or is told) is bad in it, I ſhould not have doubted of more candid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs then he expreſſes in his Book; but let us ſee what Propoſal firſt appears.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>P.</hi> firſt Propoſes, <hi>pag.</hi> 28. of his Book, <hi>That Regiſters be ſetled in every Pariſh, kept
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169891:10"/>every year by two men choſen to that work; and all Lands, Houſes and Alienations entred therein and Copies transferred to the County Town.</hi> I ſuppoſe Mr. <hi>P.</hi> means, That a Regiſtry be ſetled, &amp;c. Elſe there can be no ſence made of the firſt part of his Propoſal; I know who writes it. And therefore I ſay once for all, I ſhall not cavil at thoſe things in his Book which are ingramatical, and ſo near neighbors to nonſence; if by any means I may gueſs at his deſign and end. This Propoſal might have been ſpared, it being already under the conſideration of the Parliament, and modelled in a far better and leſs chargeable way, then this is; For what a number of Regiſters will the Nation be troubled with, if every Pariſh muſt have one, (when perhaps there will not be one Deed throughout the year, (at leaſtwiſe in ſome years) to be Recorded in ſome Pariſhes.) there muſt at leaſt be 10000 Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters, beſides the County Regiſter in the Commonwealth, for there are ſo many Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes or thereabouts in the Nation; and it will be hard to finde in every Pariſh ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny able and honeſt men as can and will be faithful in the careful tranſcribing and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring thoſe <hi>Records.</hi> To the ſecond Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169891:10"/>touching the Seal with the States Arms, I ſhall ſay nothing.</p>
            <p>The third Propoſal, is, That <hi>in every Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, every hundred yearly chuſe three men to be Peace makers, to hear and determine all common Controverſies between man and man, from whom they may not Appeal.</hi> That Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers or <hi>Dayes-men</hi> ſhould be is certainly a good thing, agreeable to the <hi>minde</hi> and <hi>will</hi> of the great <hi>Law-giver</hi> of the World, and <hi>Awards</hi> and <hi>Arbitrements</hi> are part of that Common Law which Mr. <hi>P.</hi> is ſo much againſt; but in a different way then he would have it; for we ſay, that an Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trator or Peace-maker (as he terms him) in our Law, <hi>Is a Judge indifferently choſen by both parties to end that thing which is in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies between them, and which they ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit or refer to his determination</hi> ad Arbitriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. An Arbitrator hath an <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> while he keeps cloſe to the <hi>thing ſubmitted,</hi> and <hi>ſo far</hi> there is no appeal from him, his <hi>ſentence</hi> being <hi>abſolutely</hi> concluſive, and not <hi>controulable</hi> by any <hi>Judge.</hi> But here the Peace-makers are to be <hi>choſen</hi> by the <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred</hi> in <hi>every</hi> County, and they ſhall <hi>hear</hi> and <hi>determine every Common</hi> controverſie, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the parties ſubmit their Caſes to them
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169891:11"/>or no; and that without any <hi>appeal</hi> from <hi>them,</hi> which in effect, is but thus much; <hi>Three men (be they wiſe or unwiſe, honeſt or diſhoneſt, fools or knaves, or both) ſhall be choſen by the plain and generally ignorant Countrey men of every Hundred, out of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to hear all common Controverſies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween man and man, and to judge and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine them Arbitrarily: And let them judge for fear or favor, right or wrong, their Decree or Sentence ſhall be like the</hi> Medes <hi>and</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians, <hi>it ſhall be the</hi> ne-plus ultra <hi>to every man in every Hundred.</hi> Whether this will not be of the moſt dangerous conſequence to the Commonwealth that can be, let him that hath but half an eye be the judge.</p>
            <p>In the 38. <hi>pag.</hi> of his Book, Mr. <hi>P. would have two or more Peace makers appointed in every Town, or Place or Ward to hear the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences and Civil Controverſies between man and man, before any go to Law, and if poſſible let them end it; and he would have that done only by perſwading:</hi> Surely, Mr. <hi>P.</hi> did not warily peruſe his Book after he ſet down his conceptions: This and the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent propoſition are direct contradictions.</p>
            <p>In the 28. <hi>pag.</hi> he would have no appeal from the Peace makers, but their Sentence
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169891:11"/>to de definitive; and <hi>pag.</hi> 38. he would have them onely to hear it before any go to Law, and labor to determine by perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion if they can; I have a far better opinion of his laſt Propoſal then his firſt.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>P.</hi> further ſaith, <hi>The happineſs in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment will never lie in Laws but men:</hi> But he muſt not deny but good Laws and good men together may make it more happy. And further he ſaith, That <hi>all good men carry good Laws in their boſoms:</hi> And do they out carry bad alſo? have they not a Law of Sin and Death, as well as a Law of the Spirit of life? a Law in their members as wel a Law in their mnide? We know good men err day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and the beſt of men ſometimes; there is no infallibility in their judgements, and no impoſſibility but a good man may be wrongfully byaſſed.</p>
            <p>In the 36. <hi>pag.</hi> of your Book, the ſixth head, you verifie what is ſaid next before, <hi>That there are godly men not very wiſe nor juſt:</hi> We could wiſh they all were both godly, juſt, and wiſe, that ſhould have the Judicatory Seat of deciſion and determination of mens in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and proprieties, according to the good Laws made and ordained by Parliaments, and not by Peace-makers.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:169891:12"/>
            <p>In Page 31. Section four, <hi>He tells us; All Entayls may be cut off for ever, and men have liberty to beſtow what they have, to whom they pleaſe, the Eldeſt ſon ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a double portion.</hi> Obſerve the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief and ambiguitie of this propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The miſchief of it, becauſe it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns the unſettlement of moſt eſtates in this Nation, though conveyed upon never ſo valuable a conſideration, and ſetled forty, fifty, nay a hundred years ago, yea, though (if it ſhould be cut off) the <hi>prodigal Father,</hi> or other <hi>Anceſtor</hi> have never ſo many holes in the bottom of his <hi>purſe,</hi> and be worſe then the <hi>Infidel that takes not care for his own Family;</hi> is this good councel, M.<hi>P.</hi> That poor and helpleſs children ſhould without any reſpect had to them, be deprived of a livelyhood intended and provided for them, when none was wronged, no creditor in being; and when the name of an eſtate, and not the reality of it, ſhall make the <hi>ſimple Creditor</hi> to truſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond <hi>diſcretion?</hi> for my part I think <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veat Creditor,</hi> as well as <hi>Emptor,</hi> if he truſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The ambiguity of it. Firſt, Cut of Entayls for ever, then beſtow as
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169891:12"/>you pleaſe, (That is,) Entayl your eſtate again; what ſignifies this? you muſt explain your ſelf to the world, to whoſe cenſure you have ſubmitted your book. I and ſome others may conjecture what you mean. And you ſay, the Eldeſt ſon ſhall have his double por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as it is reaſonable he ſhould; but he will be deprived, if you will have Eſtates tayl to be cut off, and the Creditor let looſe a gainſt him as well as others without reſpect; or elſe your propoſition will be partial, which a Law for publique advantage ſhould not be.</p>
            <p>In the 32. page and the head, M. <hi>P.</hi> ſayes; <hi>For a Body of Laws he knows none, but what ſhould be the reſult of ſound reaſon; nor any ſuch reaſon, but what the God of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom hath appointed; therefore the moral Law (called them ten words) is beſt, and the Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cials of</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> Solomons <hi>rules and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments added thereto.</hi> All honeſt and juſt law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers will concurr with you; but Mr. <hi>P.</hi> you know there is not in all theſe, an expreſs rule to judge every particular occurring, and contingent caſe that happens by; why then may there not be <hi>Regulae ex illis juribus ſumptae,</hi> to decide contingent caſes, (that fall not within the letter, though they fall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169891:13"/>within the meaning and generall proviſion of thoſe rules) as experience and occaſion ſhall require; I hope you will not deny but that this ought to be; then what is in our Law contrary to theſe Laws? Let that fall to the duſt, and I hope there will be none that will offer to ſupport them from falling: and Mr. <hi>P.</hi> muſt know that there is a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Law of Policy, that doth many times limit the law of nature and right reaſon, as I need make no other explanation to him then this that there is a law of God, that <hi>thou ſhalt not kill;</hi> And there is a Law of the ſame God, that thou ſhalt judicially take away mans life, where his offence is commenſurate to life. Here is natural reaſon, and the Law of God, that I ſhould not kill; and here is politick reaſon, and a Law of God, that I ſhould not withhold my hand from blood in a judicial way. M. <hi>P.</hi> doth further wiſh the Lawyers to urge theſe for Law; <hi>And not thoſe old obſolete Preſidents, which will hardly prove or make a Seamans ſute, to fit our occaſion:</hi> We urge nothing for Law that is againſt theſe, or incoherent with them; if we do, we deſire <hi>M.P.</hi> to tell us where, and prove it, and we ſhall follow his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel elſe his <hi>Ipſe dixit</hi> will not drive us out of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169891:13"/>our Reaſon, or good opinion of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Laws of this Land. What he means by <hi>our Preſidents</hi> (which for the moſt part will be juſtified to be the reſult of ſound reaſon, if he will venture a calm and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian like argument about it) <hi>not proving a Seamans ſute to fit our occaſion.</hi> I know not it is intended for a Proverb; but a very poor and perplext one, and nothing to the purpoſe to prove any thing againſt our law; if it be (I am ſure) it will hardly ſute with my underſtanding, upon this occaſion either to comprehend or Anſwer it.</p>
            <p>He ſaith next in Page 33. <hi>If any lawyer be continued, let him be allowed;</hi> and ſo page 43. Pro. 15. <hi>and let him plead for Juſtice ſake;</hi> but why not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued? is the profeſſion unlawful? ſure I am, you cannot prove it; or is it from the corruption of ſome of the profeſſors of it, that you argue againſt it? then let them be found out that are corrupt: and when they are found and Adjudged ſo, let them be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended from practice, and otherwiſe pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed according to demerit; <hi>nigro car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone notentur.</hi> But that there ſhould be no Lawyers, becauſe Fees are bottomleſs, is no Argument; and if you would have <hi>fewer</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:169891:14"/>Lawyers, be <hi>inſtant</hi> with God that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples <hi>manners</hi> may be <hi>amended</hi> and that the Goſpel may have a more influence upon them, <hi>and that men would do as they would be done unto;</hi> and then (if you and we ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in our Addreſſes to God in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect,) there will be very little need of Law or Lawyers; but while <hi>Creſcit in orbe dolus,</hi> there will be need of Law, and honeſt, and wiſe Lawyers. And we may bleſs God that provided us ſuch remedies. As for their Fees, let them be regulated, as ſhall be thought fit by the State. You are angry with them, and therefore no competent Judge over them.</p>
            <p>Page 33. Sect. 6. Mr. <hi>P.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Wills and Teſtaments may be Acknowledged by the next two Juſtices of the peace; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom they may be proved without any charge, and then entered into the former Regiſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what then? when they are acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, Do you ſuppoſe all Wills to be good then? and muſt the Juſtices be Judges and Interpreters of the Wills and Teſtaments of ſuch as deviſe eſtates? are they all through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Nation ſo quickſighted, as to diſcern the <hi>Intentions</hi> of Teſtators in their Wills?
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169891:14"/>and Judges fit to decide whether men make Wills with <hi>diſpoſing memories and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings,</hi> or no? can they with eaſe recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile the ſeeming contradictions that often happen in diyng mens Wills, by reaſon of thoſe ignorant perſons that many times they are neceſſitated to imploy to write down their Wills? are they ſo able Judges, where ſeveral Wills ariſe in competition one with the other to decide the controverſie aright, which ſhould take place? and do they know how to determine, whether, and when a Nuncupative, or a Verbal Will ſhall avoid a written Will or no? If ſo, then let the deſign of your propoſal proſper; if not, you may <hi>bluſh</hi> to propoſe a thing that will prove an apparent miſchief to the <hi>Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pag. 33. Propoſition 7. Mr. <hi>P.</hi> adviſes, <hi>That all the old Records in the Tower may be burnt as the Monuments of Tyrannie.</hi> But he proves them no ſuch thing; there may be there many uſeleſs and antiquated Records; but ſhall all be burnt for their ſakes; are there not many Records there which may give much light to this and the ſucceſſive Ages, to ſee the ſpirit and temper of many former Ages paſt. My Lord <hi>Bacon,</hi> who
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169891:15"/>I am ſure hath the eſteem of a wiſe man where his Books were known, gives a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary advice, <hi>That the ancient Volumes of the Laws ſhould not be quite extinguiſhed, but at leaſt remain in Liberaries, that in caſes of weighty conſequence, we might conſult the mutations of Laws paſt, &amp; ſprinkle modern mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with Antiquity:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bacon</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc. of Learning. pag. 452. <hi>Aph.</hi> 63.</note> what reaſon Mr. <hi>P.</hi> hath not to be of the ſame mind, I know not. I ſhould have been very glad he would have offered ſome thing to make the world believe he knew it himſelf.</p>
            <p>Pag. 34. Propoſition 8. Mr. <hi>P.</hi> propoſes, <hi>That no Lawyer might plead at any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee:</hi> but why Mr. <hi>P?</hi> nothing but a <hi>ſic volo.</hi> I will ſuppoſe it muſt be one or all of theſe three Reaſons he would give; when he will not ſet down his own reaſons. 1. That every Committee is <hi>ſo</hi> wiſe, that it is impoſſible for them to receive any ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction or information in any caſe that ſhall come before them, or in any circumſtance of any caſe, more then they of themſelves can find out. Or 2ly. That every Committee is ſo weak as to be hurried to and fro, and unſetled in their judgements by the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacies of Lawyers (and not otherwiſe, for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169891:15"/>by offering Truth, their judgements are ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and fixt;) Or 3<hi rend="sub">ly</hi>. Mr. <hi>P.</hi> muſt intend, That every man is able to manage his own Cauſe to the beſt advantage of Truth and himſelf; which I will not affirm, though he do ſo in Pag. 42. Pro. 13. But Mr. <hi>P.</hi> you will find Lawyers to be neceſſary at many Committees to plead, &amp; to help them to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome many difficult caſes that may lie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them; and you may aſſure your ſelf (if you pleaſe) it is very ſafe, many times, that for the honor of the Parliament it ſhould be ſo, if the roving and tedious Oratory of ſome Lawyers could be bounded within the <hi>due</hi> confines of the <hi>Truth</hi> of thoſe <hi>particular Caſes</hi> they <hi>handle,</hi> as they are truly circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiated.</p>
            <p>The 9. Propoſition in the ſame page, and the 18. in page 46. and the 2. in p. 35. are againſt arreſts, and impriſonments, and for <hi>Summons</hi> to be left at mens houſes; this is already anſwered by the Philizers, who have offered very ſtrong and plauſible rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for the proceſs of Arreſt, and againſt <hi>Summons;</hi> which they have publiſhed in Print, and ſubmitted to the Parliament; under whoſe conſideration it now ſtands. And I muſt tell Mr. <hi>P.</hi> That ſome of them, that have publiſhed theſe reaſons, are neither
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169891:16"/>of mean parts, Piety, or fidelity to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Government. Mr. <hi>P.</hi> would not have <hi>any</hi> put in Priſon, or <hi>puniſht with a loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Priſon,</hi> as his words are, <hi>before hearing whether he be guilty or no. i. e.</hi> before <hi>he ſay,</hi> Guilty or not Guilty: but, Sir, how many men when they are ſummoned in order to be heard, will come? eſpecially as you ſet your words, <hi>Any put in Priſon;</hi> and when they appear and are heard, how many, or rather <hi>how few</hi> will confeſs any thing againſt Themſelves, and to their own prejudice? as indeed they may not be urged to do: But in page 51. Propoſition 2. Mr. <hi>P.</hi> Seems to allow of Priſons for criminal cauſes, though before he would not have any put in Priſon.</p>
            <p>The 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Prop. in the 34. Page, is, <hi>That none ſhall diſtrain for Taxes or other Debt; but the Debtors outward door to be carryed to the Town houſe; and as many other new doors as ſhall be ſet up the ſhame and danger hereof will urge payment.</hi> Why not a diſtreſs for Taxes? is not the doors taking away a kinde of diſtreſs? But ſhould that be admitted, which you propoſe touching Taxes (becauſe it is a novelty, and may tickle the fancy of people that affect <hi>changing,</hi> and are never
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169891:16"/>well, while they are fixed, but always ſo when they can toſs and tumble themſelves in the element of Mutation) yet how can your remedy be adequate to the caſe of other Debts, can 10000 l. or 20000 l. debt, be ſpeedily got in by plucking off from a Debtors houſe the outward door? I am not able to underſtand it, and I doubt the Reader neither.</p>
            <p>Page 35. Prop. 3. <hi>Lying long in Priſon before Sentence, and delay of Juſtice, is cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:</hi> It is ſo, and I could wiſh from my ſoul it were not ſo, and that herein you would be more earneſt, and that Committees were not as much in fault as the execution of the Law in this point; and that Priſons were kept by honeſter and more conſcionable men; ſuch being indeed generally the very ſcum and refuſe of mankind; and for delay of Juſtice to men, our Law ſaith, <hi>Nulli negabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, nulli deferemus juſticiam;</hi> and for the execution of our Law, and expedition of Juſtice and Right to every man, there was never greater care than our now Judges of the Law do and have undergone.</p>
            <p>Page 36. Prop. 5, 6, 7, 8. <hi>Are in ſubſtance thus much, that you would have one or more Committees of good, Wiſe and juſt men,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169891:17"/>to receive the requeſt and advice of every particular Town and County for the obtaining of true Juſtice, and hindring of Suits; and that no man or Court of men be always above Juſtice.</hi> Sir, may not there rather be a view taken of the preſent Law, and what is good in it countenanced, and its exube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances and gray-headed errors expunged, with the advice of them that have throughly ſtudyed it, and a diſgeſt made thereof; and what it wants, ſupplyed by ſuch new Laws as it needs, it having already almoſt a ſalve for every ſoar, which is one of the moſt excellent fruits of the Age of our Law, that by running its courſe through ſo many Ages paſt, and meeting with ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive contigencies, it hath brought down Rules to us framed from experience of the former Ages: ſo that there is ſcarce a Caſe that wants a Rule of juſtice and reaſon to guide it by. I may preſume the Parliament, and moſt of the beſt of men in this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, ſee leſs need of your Committee, then what is here propoſed for the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Law.</p>
            <p>And Mr. <hi>P.</hi> ſaith, <hi>no man or Court of men are to be always above Juſtice.</hi> AIWAIES! No, not as much as ONCE above it; and yet
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169891:17"/>if you would have no Appeal from your Peacemakers. or your 5. or 7. men, in Page 39. pro. 11. They muſt in all likelihood be <hi>above</hi> juſtice, and be gratified with the <hi>priviledge</hi> of Impunity. 37. page, pro. 8. M. <hi>P.</hi> urges, <hi>That Priviledges ſhould be taken away, that bring damage or hurt to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth.</hi> This is very good; provided it be apparent that the State is prejudiced thereby; otherwiſe the priviledges of the City of London, and other great Cities and places may be impeached in that which is an apparent good to them; but until M. <hi>P.</hi> doth come out of his ſubterfuge of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, into the plain field of particulars; as we are diſabled, ſo we are not willing to give him any further anſwer in this point.</p>
            <p>Page 39 pro. 10. M. <hi>P.</hi> propoſes that to the end <hi>That Juſtice may be near to all men, that there be in every City, Town, or Hundred five or ſeven able men appointed to determine all controverſies for Debts, and Strifes, and any three of them preſent to have power to give ſentence:</hi> And afterwards he propoſes, <hi>That in weighty caſes, they may conſult with learned Advocates, and Divines.</hi> That Juſtice may run in <hi>clear ſtreams</hi> by every
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169891:18"/>mans door, it is already provided by our Law: The learned Judges, (being bred up with much expence of mony and time, and wading through a Toylſom ſtudy; and therefore knowing better to decide aright all controverſies for Debt, &amp;c. then any private Countrey Gentlemen, whom he would have to be a Committee) do ride Circuit throughout <hi>all the parts</hi> of the land to hear and determine (not arbitrarily, but by juſt rules known to the people, whereof they have had long experience,) all cauſes of <hi>what nature ſoever</hi> they be, whether <hi>Criminal</hi> or <hi>Civil.</hi> Then I pray tell us what need is there of <hi>ſuch a Committee,</hi> as you ſpeak of, and of ſuch a number of Committee men as your propoſal would have? ſeven in every City; ſeven in every Town; and ſeven in every Hundred: Many Counties in the Nation have thirty or forty Towns; beſides Cities, and Hundreds; what a number of Committee men muſt there be then in ſome Counties? at leaſt 200. and who muſt pay them Salary? muſt not the State? or will they ſerve for nought? No ſure. Sir, I muſt tell you, that you have not well conſidered what you propoſed; do you think that your propoſal can tempt men
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169891:18"/>out of their reaſons, and conveniences to embrace ſuch a dangerous <hi>trifle of novelty?</hi> No Sir. <hi>Fruſtra fit per plur a quod fieri poteſt per pauciora.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for their conſultation in <hi>weighty matters</hi> with learned <hi>Advocates</hi> and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines,</hi> the Judges in all weighty caſes do conſult <hi>again and again</hi> with learned Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates and Councellors; but with <hi>Divines</hi> they do not, except in caſes of conſcience; And I could wiſh <hi>Miniſters</hi> would forbear propoſing for themſelves, and to labour to enlarge their priviledge, to meddle beyond their <hi>own</hi> calling, which is work enough of it ſelf for them to do; this would be more profitable to their <hi>Flocks,</hi> and more honorable to <hi>themſelvs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page ibid. pro. 11. <hi>He would have no Appeal from the ſentence of theſe five, or ſeven men, but in weighty matters; and that appeal is to be from themſelves to themſelves; ſeven of them ſhall have power to reverſe or confirm the Judgement of ſeven, or a leſs number; or if yet an Appeal muſt be, it ſhall not reach out of the County, for many weighty reaſons:</hi> Thus much I underſtand of this propoſition; The greateſt part of the reſt of it is a <hi>riddle</hi> to me; but why no Appeal? and if an Appeal to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169891:19"/>the ſeven men, or if from the ſeven men, not from the Counnty? the reaſon given is: <hi>For many weighty reaſons;</hi> what a Chimera is this? I am ſorry the world ſhould be troubled (I ſay no more of it) with ſuch impertinencies.</p>
            <p>Page 43. pro. 14. <hi>Let all mens teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies be taken on oath, by notorial writings; yet ſo as witneſſes may be examined by word of mouth, each apart;</hi> The teſtimonies of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes on oath are put in <hi>writing</hi> in ſome Courts, and examined <hi>apart;</hi> and ſome other Courts by experience find it not fit ſo to do, but to examine them <hi>coram populo:</hi> where Judges, Jury, and Councel <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con</hi> watch the <hi>halting</hi> of falſe witneſſes, if they ſhould ſwear falſly; and before ſo many obſervers of their Teſtimonies falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes very rarely eſcape undiſcovered.</p>
            <p>Page 47. and 48. pro. 9. Mr. <hi>P.</hi> would have <hi>partiality prevented;</hi> then let him not ſpeak againſt the preſent Law, and its judges; for we know none more impartial, neither do we believe any can be, that ſhall come in their ſtead.</p>
            <p>Page 48. <hi>He would have great puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments inflicted on them that take gifts, or pervert Judgement:</hi> Charge any of the preſent Miniſters of the Law therewith,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169891:19"/>and prove it, and you ſhall find the Law it ſelf hath provided them pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments ſevere enough,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mag. Ch.</hi> is that <hi>nulli ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den us juſtic. &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> and more commenſurate to thoſe offences then we ſuppoſe you can offer.</p>
            <p>Page 48. pro. 20. M. <hi>P.</hi> would propoſe <hi>That ſore puniſhment be inflicted upon falſe witneſſes.</hi> The Law of England hath provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed puniſhment ſore enough for this alſo.</p>
            <p>Page 49. pro. 21. <hi>Some able men muſt be apppointed, to be ambulatory or Itinerant from Court to Court to obſerve the injuſtice of theſe ſeveral Courts that</hi> Mr. <hi>P. would have ſet up. And to inform the State of thoſe, that they may be puniſhed</hi> Mr. <hi>P.</hi> Would have ſet up in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very City, Town, and Hundred, five or ſeven able men, which in each of thoſe will (as I told the Reader) amount (in ſome Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) to 200. men and upwards: And there muſt be <hi>one</hi> in every City, Town, and Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to obſerve the Irregularities of theſe particular Committees (for I cannot ſee how it can be otherwiſe) which in the ſeveral Committees of a County (by Mr <hi>P.</hi> his rule) will amount to 30. or 40. men; for fewer cannot well obſerve the injuſtice of theſe ſeveral Committees that will conſtantly ſit. Will not this make a <hi>leane State?</hi> that it ſhould maintain <hi>all</hi> theſe officers in <hi>every</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:169891:20"/>County of the Common-wealth? there being 73. Counties in the Nation, and by Mr. <hi>P.</hi> propoſal there being near 230. or 240. officers in moſt of the ſaid Counties, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thoſe which are Counties of Cities; I think the Nation will not have much cauſe to rejoyce in ſuch a <hi>Multiplicity</hi> of officers.</p>
            <p>Page 51. Mr. <hi>P.</hi> would have <hi>no malefectors againſt the light of nature and Civil ſociety eſcape unpuniſhed, &amp;c.</hi> No more will the Laws already eſtabliſhed in the land, nor its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors; they will all approve of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal.</p>
            <p>Page 53. pro. 4. Mr. <hi>P. would have no man or Court of men to pardon any offenders; what? not any ANY</hi> offenders, let the Circumſtances or his caſe be what it will, nor <hi>no Court of men to pardon?</hi> not the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament?</hi> this is the very <hi>ſpirit</hi> and <hi>Quinteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence</hi> of Cruelty (though I think Mr. <hi>P. means</hi> it not) not warranted either by the <hi>Law of God</hi> or <hi>man,</hi> and though the next line under this propoſal be <hi>Quotations</hi> of <hi>Scripture;</hi> yet to warrant this propoſition in the <hi>latter</hi> of it by theſe Scriptures, is <hi>Humano Capiti cervicem jungere equinam;</hi> and indeed moſt of the <hi>Places</hi> of Scripture that are cited to juſtifie Mr. <hi>P.</hi> propoſitions, are <hi>extreamly miſapplied.</hi> And many times contrary to the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169891:20"/>very <hi>Tenor</hi> of what he propoſes, as if they were annexed at adventure.</p>
            <p>Page 53. pro. 5. <hi>Let no difference be made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Jew or Gentile, Bond or Free, ſtranger or Native in Criminal or Civil things, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no difference between <hi>them</hi> made by our Law in point of <hi>right between man and man;</hi> onely our Law favours a <hi>Native</hi> more then a <hi>Stranger</hi> in ſome <hi>reſpects;</hi> as if a Stranger or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lien from <hi>beyond Sea</hi> come over into this Nation, to live here and bring <hi>his children</hi> with him, and then purchaſe <hi>Lands</hi> here, thoſe children that were born beyond Sea (<hi>Ireland</hi> and ſome ſmall other <hi>Ilands</hi> where the Laws of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth are currant excepted) ſhall not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit theſe Lands; but if he hath children born here in <hi>England,</hi> they ſhall Inherit, becauſe our Laws favor Natives more then Strangers, in this reſpect; and if ſuch an Alien die without any iſſue born in this Nation, his Lands ſo purchaſed, come to the Common-wealth; but in moſt other caſes, they have equal Juſtice with other: I conceive this is not contradictory to any Law of God: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially the Alien knowing the danger of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſing Lands before hand; the other caſes in which he hath not a like priviledge with a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive (though they are but few) yet are too te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, and indeed needleſs to inſert here.</p>
            <p>Page 54. pro. 6. <hi>He propoſes that the children
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169891:21"/>and heirs of malefactors may not be puniſhed for their Fathers offences in the loſs of their eſtates that might deſcend or otherwiſe become unto them;</hi> I acknowledge it is hard, and I could wiſh with Mr. <hi>P.</hi> That the Fathers having eaten <hi>ſour grapes,</hi> the childrens <hi>Teeth</hi> may not be ſet <hi>on edge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page 56. Mr. <hi>P. propoſes that theevs for ordinary ſtealths,</hi> (I mean not Robbers upon high wayes, or Burglers) <hi>may not be ſo commonly ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged as they are.</hi> This I could wiſh alſo, (though in this there is not now ſuch ſtrictneſs obſerved as the Law preſcribes,) but that they be made <hi>Gally-ſlaves,</hi> or that ſome other ſuch courſe be taken with them, as not to take away their <hi>lives,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently <hi>all hopes</hi> of making of them better. And I ſhall <hi>fully</hi> concur with Mr. <hi>P.</hi> herein; I have ended as to Mr. <hi>P.</hi> his propoſals touching the Law, wiſhing him to <hi>conſult</hi> a <hi>little</hi> more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he writes ſo <hi>raſhly</hi> again; That which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns <hi>other</hi> profeſſions and callings, they beſt can tell how to anſwer, that are Profeſſors. I will not be, as Mr. <hi>P.</hi> is, <hi>Sutor ultra crepidam.</hi> And I have done what is here done, more haſtily then the <hi>merit</hi> and honor of the Common Law deſerves; yet I hope its profeſſors will excuſe my <hi>faults</hi> (for I conceive no other is a <hi>proper</hi> Judge of them) they being <hi>errors of love</hi> to that which is <hi>good and juſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi>Major haereditas venit unjcui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> noſtcum. a jure &amp; legibus, quam a parentibus.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
